Welcome, everybody, to the second to last
lecture of 6 .006. In this lecture, we've
mostly covered all of the testable material
that we're going to have on the final or
on quiz three. Today, really what we're
talking about is putting into context all
the material that we've learned over the
course of the term at a high level and talk
about where we can go from here in terms of
other theory classes and other classes in
the department that are related to
this material. Now, most things in the
department are in some way related to
this material. And so that's why this is a
foundational course. But we're going to
try to talk about it from a high level and
talk about how some future things that
you might be interested relate. OK. So we
started out the term in lecture one talking
about 6 .006. And we had four main goals
that we had for our course, really three
main goals. Does anyone remember what those
goals were?
There was so there was you got to the last
one first. The first one was to solve hard
computational problems, to be able to
solve problems. So this is kind of like the
let's make an algorithm part of the course,
one solve hard computational problems.
I guess hard here maybe should be in quotes
because we saw in the last lecture what
hard means in the technical sense.
Hard could mean that there's no efficient
algorithm that we know how to solve
a problem on. That's getting a little bit
ahead of ourselves. Computational problems
with algorithms is really the key part
about this goal. It's kind of the same goal
that you have in a class like 6 .0001. Or
6 .009, right? You're trying to convince a
computer that you solved a problem on a
finite set of inputs. But really what this
class is about is two other things which is
more about communication to people rather
than computers. Right? Your algorithm might
be correct or efficient, but you need to be
able to communicate that to humans. And
that's what the other two goals are.
So second one is argue correctness.
Basically that the thing that I'm doing to
my inputs is always going to lead me to a
correct output. No matter what input I
give it, any valid input, there could be an
infinite space of possible inputs. And in
this class, that's the case because we want
our input size to grow arbitrarily large.
We need to be able to argue correctness
that it's going to return me the correct
thing no matter what my inputs are. And in
order to do that, that's essentially 6
.042. This whole class has basically been
applied 6 .042. I've given you some
procedures, and you have to prove things
about these procedures. Or most of the
time, we proved it for you, and then you've
used them as black boxes. But
that's a lot of what this class is about.
And the third one is efficiency. Argue
that it's good, for lack of a better thing.
This is efficiency. What does good
mean? Well, that was hard to know at the
beginning of our class. And so we set up
this model of computation, a framework
through which we could determine how good
or bad our algorithms were by defining a
model of computation, saying what things
we can do in constant time, and then just
building off of that. So this is basically
our model plus some asymptotics or
something like that.
Ran out of space. What? It's
about scalability. Yeah, this is about
scalability. This is a model of computation
tells us how much time we can spend, but
it's compared to our inputs. This is always
about, how does our algorithm perform
relative to the rate that our problem size
grows? And so that's what we mean by good.
And in this class, we don't tend to talk
about constant size problems. It's about
how algorithms can scale as you have
arbitrarily large inputs. That's why we
need recursion and induction to be
able to prove things about our algorithms,
and that's why we need this relative
to input size, the growth factor of our
algorithm's performance relative to the
input. And then the last thing is kind of,
to me, one of the most important things,
is communicating these things to another
human. So communication
is key here. Right? If you can always write
good code that's always right, good for
you. I can't do
that all the time.
But that might mean that you can be very
competent, independent computer programmer.
Right? But you're going to be limited in
what you can do if you're only able to rely
on yourself. Right? A lot about computer
science is working with others to solve
computational problems. And when you're
working with others to solve computational
problems, you need to be able to
communicate with them, and you need to be
able to communicate them both what it is
you're doing and why it is you're doing it.
Right? That you're doing the correct thing
and that it's efficient. Right? And so
that's a big part about what this course
is. It's, at the end of the day, on your
quiz, if you write down Python script for a
correct algorithm, but we don't know what
it's doing, but it's correct, we're not
going to give you full points on that
because you're not satisfying the
conditions of this class. Right? It's
really about the communication here. OK. So
just to review, since we've not discussed
how the most recent lecture fits into your
problem set, we didn't have any problem
sets that covered complexity.
So how does that fit in? Well, argue that
the ways that we're solving our problems
are good. What we proved in the last
lecture was that most problems cannot be
solved good. Right? They can't be solved
in polynomial time with respect to the size
of your input. However, most of the
problems that we think about, in a sense, I
can prove to you that it's a yes solution.
I can show you a simple path in this graph
that has a certain length, or I can show
you a subset that sums to a certain value
in a particular problem. I can give you
a certificate that I can prove to you in a
reasonable amount of time that, yes, I can
prove to you that the answer to this thing
is correct. And that's what we
talked about in the last lecture.
Not always good
algorithms to solve problems.
But many
problems
we think about can
be either checked
in polynomial time.
This is the concept of having a certificate
that I could give you of polynomial size
that could be checked in polynomial time.
Right? In a sense, that's a way checked in
polynomial time. This leads to our class of
decision problems, NP. Or can be solved by
brute force in exponential time. Right?
Most of the things that we've talked about
in this class fall into one of these two
categories. Right? We can just brute force
over the combinatorial space of possible
outputs and check to see if they're
correct. Right? Or I can give
you a certificate basically saying,
look, I can solve actually anything that's
of this form can be checked in this form
because there's only a polynomial number of
things to check. Or sorry, an exponential
possible number of certificates of
polynomial length to check. But basically,
this is saying that the problems that
we think of mostly fall into these two
categories. And so there usually are
algorithms to solve the problems that we
care about.
For the purposes of the final, you'll be
able to see on your final exam practice
problems that we're going to give you. Most
of what we cover in terms of material on
the final that will be testing the lecture
19 material will be in terms of these
definitions. Do you understand what the
decision problem class NP is? EXP is? They
just relate to each other. EXP is
definitely a superset of NP here. Right? NP
nestles inside here. They could be equal,
probably not. Right? Those are the types of
things that we would address knowing kind
of a directionality of a reduction. Right?
If you have a problem A and a problem
B, right? And I know that this one is
difficult by some measure. Right? I already
happen to know that it's very hard, right?
Like NP hard or something like that. If
this is a problem that I'm interested in
knowing the complexity about, and I can
prove that I can solve it if I had a black
box to solve B, any black box to solve
B, and I could make this reduction in
polynomial time. And if this is
hard, that means this can't be solved.
That means that if this is hard, then
I better not be able to solve this in
polynomial time. Right? Because then I
would be able to solve this in polynomial
time. So that's basically the type of
argument usually in a true -false question
we might have on the final exam for you
to kind of understand the basic high -level
definitions involved in what was talked
about in lecture 19. Hardness, right? The
very most difficult problems of these
classes. And completeness, sorry, anything
harder than things in these classes, where
completeness is the ones that are in this
set, but at least as hard as anything in
those classes. OK? So that's just to give
you a brief overview of the only material
that hasn't been tested, but might be
tested on the final. OK? So when we don't
have a good algorithm, we can actually
prove that it probably doesn't have a good
algorithm. And that's kind of a problem
that you'll be able to solve in future
classes if you continue along this track.
OK. So what's the actual content that
we talked about? And this is a very high
-level overview of why we're taking this
class, why you're taking this class. Right?
But what is the content we actually
covered? I like to break it up into three
units.
In a sense, two subunits.
So quiz one material
and quiz two material
was about showing you some nice black
boxes. Right? Basically, if I'm going to
have inputs of non -constant size, it's
going to be useful for me to be able to
find things among those elements. Right? So
that's really what quiz one is all about.
Right? Data structures
for finding things
in non -constant size database.
And then, in restoring these things, we
want to support maybe two different types
of queries.
Ones that were intrinsic to the items, what
the items were. And ones based on what an
extrinsic order was placed on these items.
Right? And that was a way in which we broke
down, how should I approach looking at
this problem? I want to be able to support
queries and maintain an extrinsic order
on these things. I might want to sequence.
Right? This is a sequence
extrinsic order.
Or I want to be able to look up, is this
thing in my set? Right? By a key that we
identify it with, a unique key.
Right? So this is some intrinsic queries.
And often, order.
Not all, like a hash table doesn't maintain
any order on my keys. Right? But it does
support intrinsic queries. Is this thing in
my set or not? But we did show you other
set data structures that do support an
intrinsic order that allows me to see what
the next larger and next previous, the next
larger or the next smaller item is in my
set. Right? So here's a summary of those
data structures that we had. I'm not going
to go into how to use these things or how
to choose from among them here. That's what
your quiz one review lecture was all about.
Right? But basically, the idea here is if
we have a sequence, most of the time when
you're programming, being able to push and
pop at the end of a list is pretty
good. Which is why in Python, the most
fundamental data structure that you have is
a list. Because it's a super useful thing.
I just want to store a bunch of things,
have random access to the, say, 10th
element to my thing. But I'm not
necessarily having to dynamically update
the order of these things dynamically. I
don't necessarily have to insert something
in the middle of the list. But most of the
time, what I can do is put it at the end of
the list and maybe swap it down into place
if I need to. Right? So that's why a list
is super useful. A sequence AVL tree,
useful, but not as ubiquitous as a linked
list. I mean, as a dynamic array. Sorry.
I said linked list. I meant Python list,
which is a dynamic array. OK. So the
dynamic array tended to be, in your coding
practice, your most common sequence data
structure here. So we can get pretty good
for this insert in the middle operation
with the sequence AVL. OK. Then on the set
data structure side, I kind of categorize
these things into a couple different
categories here in terms of the operations
we can support on these things. These are
all intrinsic operations, finding things,
inserting, deleting things. I think of the
first three as being dictionary operations.
Right? I want to just look up whether
something's there. The last two are order
-preserving operations, where it matters
what the order these things are stored in.
And so as you can see from the asymptotic
complexity of the various operations here,
the hash table is actually super good if
you just want to support dictionary
operations. But in the cases where you need
to maintain order dynamically, a set AVL
is the way to go. Right? But if you don't
need it dynamic, but you still need those
order operations, a sorted array is just
good enough if you don't need to change
what they are. Right? So that's a quick
overview of quiz one type data structures
material. But then we used most of these
data structures to get faster sorting
algorithms in different contexts. Right?
So the first thing on this list involved
making a data structure and exploiting that
data structure to get a better running
time, all except for merge sort, really.
Right? The first two we presented in terms
of a priority queue. Right? Whether we used
a sorted array or an array, we re
-represented it at the end of lecture eight
to get n squared running time. We
generalized that down to n log n. By using
a heap, that was a nice optimization.
But we also got interesting data structures
using an AVL. I mean, interesting sorting
algorithms using an AVL tree because of the
power of maintaining a dynamic order over
time. But then exploiting a direct access
array to be able to sort in linear time
for small bounded in terms of the input,
polynomially bounded in terms of the input,
ranges of numbers. Right? So we leveraged
that direct access array to get counting
sort. And then we kind of amplified that
effect by sorting on a bunch of digits
multiple times to get basically polynomial
blow up in terms of the numbers that we
could sort in linear time. OK? So that's an
overview of the content
of quiz one. In quiz two,
we were kind of like, OK, now you know how
to find things within a set of just a flat
list of things. Right? You can put it in a
data structure. But in a sense, a graph is
a special kind of data structure that
relates the different things in your input.
Right? So if you've got a bunch of
vertices, there's a relation now between
those vertices that are your edges. And
then you can use full framework in talking
about discrete systems because you can
think of a vertex as a state of your system
and then connect these transitions as
a graph. Right? The reason why, I mean,
graphs are awesome. Right? But they're
awesome because they can be used to model
so many different things within our world.
Right? It's not just about road networks.
Right? It can also be about playing
your favorite turn -based game. Right? Like
tilt. Right? OK. So we talked about a lot
of different types of problems that you
could solve, various algorithms, with
a focus on a bunch of different ways of
solving single source shortest paths. And
again, just like the sorting algorithms and
just like the data structures, we presented
multiple of them because we had this trade
-off of generality of the graph that
they apply to contrasted with their running
time. Right? So I guess in particular, the
top line there is, in some sense, the most
restrictive. We don't have any cycles in
our graph. That's a very special type of
graph. And we're
able to get linear time.
But then even if we do have cycles in our
graph, we can do better if we have a bound
on the weights in our thing, whether
there's an easy conversion to a linear time
algorithm via an unweighted process. Or
whether these things are non -negative, so
there can't be negative weight cycles
and we don't have to deal with that. OK. So
that's quiz two material. And then quiz
three material was kind of applying this
graph material to a recursive framework.
What was our recursive framework? Everyone
say it with me. Dynamic programming. And
the framework was sort bot. Right? Missing
a letter, but sort bot. Right? So we think
of the quiz three material as really an
application of the graph material. Right?
What are we doing in sort bot? We're
defining a set of subproblems.
This is a set of vertices in a graph. What
is the relationship doing? It's saying,
what are the relation between the
subproblems? Right? Essentially, defining
the edges of a graph. Right? And then this
topological order and the base cases, all
of these things are just saying, what is
the problem that I want to solve on this
graph? And how do I compute that for things
that don't have any outgoing edges? Right?
I need to start writing the board again.
This is graphs. There was sorting in here,
too. This is basically
an application.
OK. Graphs was basically a relationship
on these non -constant things.
So this was kind of like useful black
boxes. Right? That you can just bundle up
and stick in some inputs, stick out some
outputs, and you're golden. Right? Whereas
quiz three was very different. The
material in quiz three is very different.
Subproblems that will be able to be related
in a recursive way. So you can solve the
problem. This is a very much more difficult
thing than these other things, I think,
because there's a lot more creativity
in this. Right? In the same way that just
applying, reducing to the graph algorithms
that we have is fairly easy, but actually
doing some graph transformations to change
the shape of the graph so that you can
apply these algorithms, that's a harder
thing to do. The difficulty with these two
sets of materials is very similar. Figuring
out what the graph should be, figuring out
what the subproblems should be, and how
they relate is really the entire part of
the entire difficulty with solving problems
recursively. Right? And we've only given
you a taste of solving problems
recursively. In future classes, like 6046,
which is the follow on to this one in the
undergraduate curriculum, this is all about
introduction to algorithms. The next one's
about design and analysis of algorithms.
Right? It's quite a bit more difficult
because we've mostly left it to you to use
the things that we gave you or make
your own algorithms based on this very nice
cookbook -like framework that you can plug
in a recursive algorithm to. Now, actually,
that cookbook is super nice for any way of
looking at a problem recursively. But while
in dynamic programming, the inductive
hypothesis of combining your subproblems is
almost trivial. Right?
So if you're looking at all types
of recursive algorithms, that's not
necessarily the case. OK? Especially when
instead of looking at all possible choices,
for example, in a greedy algorithm where
you're just looking at one of the choices,
the locally best thing, and recursing
forward, you're not doing all the work.
Right? You're not locally brute forcing.
You're locally picking an optimal thing
locally and hoping that
it'll lead you to a good thing.
And so that's a very good thing to operate
under. And so that's more like the material
that you'll be talking about in 6046. OK?
So that's 006, a very quick overview of the
content of this class. And we really like
the structure of how this class is laid out
because it gives you a fundamental idea of
the things people use to store information
on a computer. And a sense of how you solve
problems computationally and how to argue
that they're correct and efficient. Right?
That's really what this course is about.
And if you feel like you enjoy this kind
of stuff, that's where you go to take 6046.
Right? And 6046 was actually the first
algorithms class I ever took here at MIT.
As a grad student, actually,
this was hard for me. It's actually hard to
look at these problems, these types, and
think in a computational way, especially
having not taken this class, 6006. So
hopefully you guys are all in a better
position than I was when I took it. There's
two ways I like to think of the content in
6046. One is kind of just as an extension
of 006. Right? It's the natural follow
on to the things that we do in this class.
Right? They still talk
about data structures.
This isn't the core part of 046, but
they do touch on data structures for more
complicated, that have more complicated
analysis involved in them. It's really
about, usually in 046, stating what the
algorithm is doing is not so hard. Right?
Basically, giving you the algorithm, number
one here, is not so difficult to state
what's happening in the algorithm. But the
number two and number three here, arguing
that that thing is correct and arguing
that thing is efficient, that's where the
complexity comes in in 046. The analysis
part is quite a bit more complicated in 046
than in 006. Right? So they solve a problem
called union find and give a much, we
talked a little bit about amortization.
This goes into a much better, a much more
formal way of proving things run in
amortized time. OK? So this is basically
amortization via what
we call a potential analysis.
It's basically making that notion that we
talked about when we were talking about
dynamic arrays of, we're not doing this
expensive thing too often. Basically, what
we do is we keep track of the cost of all
sequence of operations and prove that the
average cost is small. Right? That's kind
of what this potential analysis is doing.
It's a little bit more formal process for
making that argument a little more formal.
Right. OK. So then on the graph side, this
is kind of an extension of quiz one type
material. This is, what is this union find
data structure? It's basically, it's a set
type thing, right, where I can make a set
of just a single element. I can take two
sets, merge them together, make them their
union. Right? And then given an object, I
say, which set am I part of? Right?
Essentially by electing a leader within a
set and saying, return me a pointer to that
one. Right? And so this can be useful in
dynamically maintaining, say, the connected
components in a dynamically changing
graph,
supporting the query of, am I in the same
component as this other guy? Right? That
could be a very useful thing to know about
a graph as it's changing. So that's an
application of this problem. And they
get near constant performance for a lot of
these queries. It's not quite, but pretty
close. OK. On the graph side, they solve a
number of very useful problems on graphs.
Minimum spanning tree. So I'm trying to
find a tree connecting all of the vertices
in a connected component of my graph. And
I'm trying to find, in a weighted graph,
I'm trying to find the spanning tree that
has minimum total weight. Right? So
that's a problem, a fundamental problem in
weighted graph algorithms. They've
solved this via a greedy algorithm. OK? And
network flows.
And I guess cuts. So this is, what is
this? This is, I'm given a weighted graph.
Basically, each of the weights correspond
to a capacity. I could push water through
along this edge. Right? And I may be given
a source vertex and a sink vertex. Right?
And I want to say, I want to shove water
through the source vertex along the edges
with their various capacities. And I'll get
some amount of water on the other end in
the source. Right? So the question is,
what's the most amount of water that I can
push through this? Well, I could build that
pipe network with the different things and
just do this experimentally. I just stick
a bunch of, maybe, I'm a mechanical
engineer. So that maybe makes sense to
me. But you want to be able to just look at
those numbers And then you can tell me how
much water I can push through. That's what
the max flow in a network is talking about.
And we give you some polynomial time
algorithms in this class. Basically,
incremental algorithms that, kind of like
Dijkstra, or kind of like Bellman -Ford,
will incrementally update estimates of a
max flow
And then on the,
basically, design paradigms,
you've got more involved making your
own divide and conquer algorithms, dynamic
programming algorithms,
greedy algorithms. Basically, they go a
lot more in depth in terms of how to design
these algorithms and these paradigms than
we do in this class. OK? And then the last
thing is we only touched on complexity. And
in a sense, 046 is only going to touch on
complexity. It's a very big field. Right?
But it will give you the tools to be able
to prove that something is NP -hard. Kind
of say that, oh, there's this thing called
a reduction. We didn't give you any
problems in which you actually had to
reduce one problem to another. And you'll
do a lot more of that here. So reductions.
So in a big sense, 046 is really just a
natural extension to the 006 material, plus
some additional stuff, which I'm going to
get to in a second. Yeah, question? Do you
want to add randomization for ? JASON KUO -
I'm going to talk about that slightly in a
separate. I'll get to your question in
just a second. I like to think of it as a
separate topic, which I'll go into right
now. The separate topic, I like to think of
it as instead of being the natural
extension to the things in the 006 units,
what I'm going to do is kind of relax
either what it means to have a correct
algorithm or relax what it means to what
my model of computation is. So 006, this is
kind
of as an extension
of 006. And this is
kind of like 6046 as,
you know, change
my definition of what it
means to be correct or efficient.
So
we've already kind of done this a little
bit in 006. I'm going to basically, one of
the things that we can do, which is
what the question that the student asked a
question about, was about randomized
algorithms, which is a big part of 046,
actually. Randomized analysis of algorithms
that are not deterministic, right? It's
not guaranteed that it'll give you the same
output every time or not guaranteed that
it will do the same computations over the
course of the algorithm every time. But it
exploits some randomization.
And in 006, we've mostly not touched on
this except in one area. Where did we use
randomization? In hashing, right? When we
used hashing, what were we doing? What did
we change the definition of correct versus
efficient? We didn't really change the
definition. What we did was we said that it
was OK that sometimes our algorithm was
slower. Then then then on in expectation,
right? That's what we we meant there. We're
relaxing the idea of efficient, but we're
still saying it's good because most of the
time it is good, right? So this there's two
types of randomized algorithms. They have
these weird names based on betting regions
of the world, shall we say. There are.
This is L. Oh, Las Vegas. It is Las Vegas
algorithms. These are always correct.
But probably efficient.
In a sense, that's what hashing is, right?
I'm always going to give you the right
thing, right? Whether this thing is in
my set or not. But some of the time, it's
inefficient, right? I have to look through
a chain of length of that's linear in the
size of the things that I'm storing. OK?
And this is in contrast to a Monte Carlo
algorithm,
which is always efficient
for some definition of efficient,
but only probably correct.
And I mean, I could define you a hash table
that has Monte Carlo semantics instead,
right? Say, for example, I say that I'm
going to it's going to be exactly the same
as a hash table, except instead of storing
all the things that collide in a place, I
just store the first two, say, right?
Well, actually, that's actually going to be
always efficient. I'm going to look through
the things and see if it's in there. And
the chains that I'm storing there only
have two things. It's going to be always
efficient. It's always going to give me
constant time. But some of the time, it's
going to be the wrong thing, because
I'm not storing everything in that chain,
right? So there's some probability that
that's not going to be correct, right? And
so that's a different kind of how if maybe
I want my hash tables to always be fast,
but I can afford to be wrong some of the
time. I don't know. In practice, this is
actually sometimes a good trade -off in
real systems. Sometimes it's OK to be wrong
some of the times if we
get good performance.
OK. But generally,
can do better if you
allow randomization.
And by better, I mean, usually, we can get
faster bounds on a lot of problems if we
allow randomization and things aren't
necessarily always correct or always
efficient. OK? So this is a big area in
046 that requires a lot more analysis using
randomness and
probability. So if you
need some primers on that, we didn't have a
lot of this in 006. But if you can do this
stuff, and you can get it to the right
thing, that's going to give you a lot of
time to think about how you want to use it.
And so that's why I say, look, if you want
to do everything from 06 to 046, that's
going to be a really important thing for
you to brush up on. OK? The next part on
006 is kind of changing what our definition
of correct or efficient means. I mean,
we've restricted ourselves in this class to
a class of problems where we
only talk about integers, right?
number is. And I can't even store a real
number on my computer. So what the hell,
Jason? What are you talking about? I can't
do that on a computer. But what I can do is
basically compute things in a
numerical sense, numerical algorithms.
And in 046, a lot of times we put this in
the context of continuous optimization.
Continuous being the opportune word here,
not discrete systems. You have a continuum
of possible solutions, real numbers
essentially. How do we do this on a
computer that's
a discrete system?
Basically, in 046, what you can do, and in
other numerical methods classes, what you
can say is, well, I know that you can't
return me a real number. I got that. Or you
can maybe have a model of computation that
allows integers to represent other kinds of
real numbers, like radicals or rationals
or something like that. And I can do
manipulations on those. But really
what these algorithms are usually about is
computing real numbers, not completely, but
to some bounded precision. And I pay for
that precision. The more bits of precision
I want on my number, I have to pay for
them. So this is, I think of these as an
approximation of real number to some
precision.
So I can say, for
precision with time.
So let's say I want to compute the square
root of a number. I could have an algorithm
just like the algorithms or, I guess,
division, long division. You all know the
algorithm of long division. You put the
quotient under here with these, an a, b,
and you get the c on top or whatever.
That's an algorithm. That's a procedure
using essentially small numbers. I'm only
talking about the digits 0 to 9 here when
I'm doing that algorithm. So it's a
procedure that only uses small integers to
compute arbitrary
precision of a division.
So that's an algorithm. And I have to
pay time to get more digits. So that's an
example of this kind of how we live in the
world of real numbers when all we have is a
discrete system. And then the last kind
of category I'd like to talk about here is
really approximation algorithms.
Whereas this is kind of an approximation
algorithm. I'm approximating my outputs.
This is an approximation algorithm from the
state standpoint of, well, there's a lot
of problems that I can't solve efficiently.
They're NP -hard. They're in EXP or even
harder problems. But maybe I'm OK with not
getting the optimal solution. So this is in
the domain of
optimization problems.
So most of the dynamic programming
problems that we gave you were optimization
problems or the shortest paths problems.
Those are optimization problems. Basically,
the possible outputs are ranked in some
way, the distance of a path that you return
or something like that. They're ranked in
some way. There's an optimal one, the one
with the smallest metric or something like
that. Well, in an approximation algorithm,
what I do is, OK, I get that it's
computationally difficult for you to give
me the longest path. Simple path in this
graph or the shortest possible route for my
traveling salesman. But maybe that's OK. I
mean, my engineering spidey sense tells me
that within 10 % is fine. So maybe instead
of giving me the most optimal thing, can I
give you an algorithm that's guaranteed
to be within a certain distance from the
optimal thing? Usually, we're looking for
constant factor approximations, which is
low constant or maybe even have to do for
worse if such things don't exist. OK, so
that's approximation algorithms. Can we get
close to an optimal solution in polynomial
time? And then the last way we could
change things in especially future classes,
though sometimes they talk about this in
046 as well, is we could change the model
of computation. We could basically change
something in our computer to be put in some
other weird paradigm of solving problems
with more power, essentially. Or you're in
a situation where there's less power. OK,
so change in the model of computation.
OK,
so what we've been talking to you in terms
of model of computation is our word ramp.
Word ramp.
That essentially says I can do arithmetic
operations, and I can look up stuff in my
memory in constant time. But if I allocate
a certain amount, I have to pay that amount
and that kind of thing. So that's this word
ramp model. But in actuality, all of your
computers, it's a lot easier for me to
figure, to find and read memory that's on
my CPU in a register than it is for me to
go out to the hard disk, ask this, well, in
my day, it used to be this movable
mechanical head that had to go and scan
over a bit on a CD -ROM drive
and actually read what that thing was.
So we can add complexity to our model to
better account for the costs of operations
on my CPU.
And that's the slowest thing to access. And
I can put a cost associated with each of
those things. And instead of
having all of our operations be
said to be constant, the constants are
actually different, and I have to pay for
that difference. And so that's extending
our model to be a little bit more realistic
to our machine. Another one is we
have computers right now that operate in
classical physics. Right? That exploit
things in classical physics. But in
actuality, our world allows for even
more complicated types of operations, like
quantum operations, where you're exploiting
entanglement and superposition of
different atoms to potentially get
operations that I can act on my data that
are actually provably stronger than the
classical models in some sense. Right? So
this is the whole huge reason why there's
a lot of work being done in, say, lots of
industry research facilities in figuring
out these models. Because maybe if you can
make a big enough quantum computer, you can
break encryption and stuff in polynomial
time. And that's something that maybe the
NSA is interested in. And I'm not going to
go into that. But you know,
some people, you look at artificial
intelligence and things like discussions
around artificial intelligence, my brain
might be doing things that a classical
computer cannot. Right? It could be
using quantum superposition in some way.
In some sense, our brains are more
powerful. And so a lot of what AI should be
looking into is what is the actual model of
computation of our brains that can give us
the power to have sentience. So that's
quantum computing. I don't know much about
it, actually. And then there's things
like maybe I have more than one CPU.
All the computers you have, even the
ones in your phone, probably have multiple
cores. In a sense, you have lots of
CPUs running in parallel. So this is like
there's one R in parallel.
Parallel computing basically says, it's
cheap for me to make another computer,
potentially. If I have two computers
running on the same problem, maybe I can
get a twofold speedup on the time in which
it takes to solve my problem. Now, that's
not accurate. I mean, suppose I had then
100 CPUs running on a machine. Maybe I can
get a hundredfold speedup. And actually,
in real life, a hundredfold speedup makes a
difference. It's am I waiting for this for
10 minutes, or am I waiting for this for 1
,000 minutes? That's like all day. I don't
want to do that. Maybe it's on weeks. I
don't even remember. But parallel
computing, if I can get a hundredfold
speedup, that might be a huge win. But for
some problems, it's not possible. If I have
k CPUs, can I get a k factor speedup? It's
not always possible to do. And so parallel
computing is another paradigm in which
there's a lot of interesting theory going
on. There's a lot of complications there
because there are a couple of different
models. You could have a multi -core setup
where you have a lot of computers that are
accessing the same bank of memory. And then
you don't want them all to be reading and
writing from them at different times
because you don't necessarily know what
their state is. And you get these
collisions, which are something that you
really have to think about in this world.
Or you have situations where maybe I have a
bunch of nanoflies or something that
are going around. And they have very small
computer brains themselves.
But they can talk to each other and pass
information to each other. But they don't
have access to one central network
repository of information. That's what we
call a distributed parallel system where
all of the CPUs that you have can interact
with each other maybe locally but don't
have access to the same memory system. So
they have to work together to learn
information about the system. OK. So that's
a brief overview of the different
directions this class, 6 .006 and theory in
general, could lead you into a huge
array of different branches of theory and
different problems that you could address
with different types of computers. OK. So I
know this is a very high level lecture. And
maybe less applied than some of you might
like. But I hope this gives you a good
understanding of the directions you can go
after this class that I think are really
exciting in terms of how to solve problems
computationally. OK. So
with that, I'd like to end there.